<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The duties of constables, borsholders, tythingmen, and such other lowe ministers of the peace wherevnto be also adioined the seuerall offices of church-wardens, of surueiors for amending the high waies, of distributors of the prouision for noisome foule and uermine, of the collectors, ouerseers, and gouernors of the poore, and of the wardens and collectors for the houses of correction / collected and penned by William Lambard ... 1582.</title>
            <author>Lambarde, William, 1536-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24187405</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24187405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27340</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04997)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27340)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1819:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The duties of constables, borsholders, tythingmen, and such other lowe ministers of the peace wherevnto be also adioined the seuerall offices of church-wardens, of surueiors for amending the high waies, of distributors of the prouision for noisome foule and uermine, of the collectors, ouerseers, and gouernors of the poore, and of the wardens and collectors for the houses of correction / collected and penned by William Lambard ... 1582.</title>
                  <author>Lambarde, William, 1536-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Roger VVarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸ F³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Constables --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27340:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27340:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Duties of Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles Borsholders, Tything<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſuch other lowe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Peace.</p>
            <p>Wherevnto be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dioined the ſeuerall offices of Church-wardens: <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rueiors for amending the high waies: of Diſtributors of the prouiſion for noiſome Foule and Vermine: of the Collectors: Ouerſeers: and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of the Poore: and of the Wardens and Collectors for the houſes of Correction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected and penned by <hi>William Lambard</hi> of Lincolnes Inne Gent. 1582.</p>
            <p>¶ Printed at London, by <hi>Roger VVarde.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27340:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27340:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DVTIES OF CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, Borſholders, Tythingmen, and ſuch other lowe miniſters of the Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderſtanding by ſundrie friends of mine,<note place="margin">1. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie well diſpoſed men doo earneſtly wiſh, that ſome one ſhort and plaine col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection might be made of the dueties of high Conſtables, petie Conſtables, Borſholders, Tythingmen Headborrowes, and ſuch like inferiour miniſters of the Quéenes Maieſties peace, to the end that when any of them ſhould be called to any of the ſaid offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (or the like) they might the better behaue themſelues in doing the ſame: I haue thought it a thing woorthie the labour, to ſend abroad among them this little treatiſe, which I haue drawne to ſatiſfie in ſome part their honeſt deſire:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27340:3"/>
hartilie praieng vnto God, that as their knowlege may be increaſed in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereof, ſo alſo their diligence may be amended in the practiſe of the ſame, to the ſetting forth of the glorie of God, and to the aduancement of the Quéenes Maieſties ſeruice in this behalfe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">The diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this worke.</note>
               <hi>2</hi> And bicauſe I purpoſe (by the helpe of God) to make this worke ſo ſhort, and ſo plaine withall, as the matter therof it ſelfe will ſuffer me, and as the vnderſtanding of vnlearned men doth require: I will firſt ſpeake ſomewhat, both of the ſundrie names and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of theſe officers, and then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward I will go in hand with the parts of their ſeuerall duties.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">The names of theſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note>
               <hi>3</hi> The ſundrie names of <hi>Conſtables,</hi> or high Conſtables that be of Lathes, Rapes, Wapentakes, Hundreds, and Franchiſes: and the diuers names alſo of <hi>Conſtables,</hi> petie Conſtables, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingmen, Borſholders, Boroeheads, Headboroes, chiefe pledges, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (if there be any) that beare office in townes, pariſhes, hamlets, tythings, or boroes (for of Conſtables of Caſtels, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called Caſtellanes, and ſuch
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27340:3"/>
others I meane not to intreate) are all in effect but two, that is to ſay, <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> and <hi>Borſholders:</hi> for theſe two words do containe as much as all the reſt of thoſe names, and to theſe two may al the reſt of them be wel brought: and therefore, in ſpeaking ſeuerally of theſe two, I will paſſe along, and touch all the reſt alſo.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> The name <hi>Conſtable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables name.</note> is made (as I haue read) of two Engliſh words put togither, namely, <hi>Cuning)</hi> or <hi>Cyng)</hi> and <hi>Staple,</hi> which doe ſignifie, the ſtay (or hold) of the king. For by the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of this realme, there is a great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer called the <hi>Conſtable</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who by meanes of the great auctoritie that he had, was a principall ſtaie vnto the <hi>Kings</hi> gouernement:<note place="margin">13 R. 2. cap. 12.</note> and this man had iuriſdiction and auctoritie in déedes of <hi>Armes,</hi> and in matters of war, both within and without the <hi>Realme.</hi> Out of which office, this lower <hi>Conſtable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> was at the firſt drawn and fetched, and is (as it were) a verie finger of that ſame hand.<note place="margin">13. E. 1.</note>
               <note place="margin">His be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</note> For the ſtatute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> which was made in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and by which theſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27340:4"/>
lower <hi>Conſtables</hi> of hundreds &amp; Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes were firſt ordained, doth (amongſt other things) appoint, that for the better kéeping of the peace, two <hi>Conſtables</hi> in euerie <hi>Hundred</hi> and <hi>Franchiſe,</hi> ſhoulde make the view of <hi>Armour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, the name of <hi>Conſtable</hi> in a hundred or franchiſe doth meane, that hee is an <hi>Officer</hi> that ſupporteth the <hi>Queenes Maieſtie</hi> in the maintenance of hir peace, within the precinct of his hundred, or franchiſe: and he is manie times called the <hi>High</hi> Conſtable, in compariſon of the <hi>Conſtables,</hi> or <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Conſtables</hi> that be in the townes or pariſhes within his hundred or fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, whoſe part it is likewiſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the peace within the ſeuerall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their owne townes or pariſhes.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Borſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders name.</note>
               <hi>5</hi> As touching <hi>Borſholder,</hi> which is the other generall name and doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine within it the men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of <hi>Tything<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> Borrowheades, Headborrowes, Thirdborrowes, and chiefe pledges, that alſo is made vp of theſe two Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh worde, <hi>Borhes,</hi> and <hi>Ealdor;</hi> of the which, <hi>Borhes</hi> betokeneth pledges, and <hi>Ealdor</hi> ſignifieth the <hi>Chiefe,</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27340:4"/>
or the <hi>Elder:</hi> and ſo <hi>Borheſealdor</hi> in one word, doth meane the chiefe, or head of the ſuerties, or pledges.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> But now,<note place="margin">His two offices.</note> that you may the better vnderſtand what is ment by this, you muſt further know, that euerie of theſe <hi>Borſholders,</hi> Tythingmen, Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, Headborrowes, Thirdborrows, and chiefe pledges, hath two ſeuerall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices at this day: the one being his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and firſt office, and the other his latter made office.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">Archai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onomia</note>
               <hi>7</hi> His firſt office began thus:<note place="margin">His firſt office.</note> by the ancient lawes of this realme (before the comming in of King <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour</hi>) it was ordeined for the more ſure kéeping of the peace, and for the better repreſſing of théeues &amp; robbers, that al frée borne men ſhould caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into ſeuerall companies, by ten in ech companie: and that euery of thoſe ten men of the companie, ſhuld be ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and pledge for the foorth-comming of his fellowes: ſo that if any harme were done by any of theſe ten againſt the peace, then the reſt of the ten ſhould be amerced, if he of their companie that did harme ſhould flie, &amp; were not forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27340:5"/>
to anſwere to that wherwith he ſhould be charged.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe theſe companies be yet in ſome plates of England (&amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with vs in <hi>Kent</hi>) called <hi>Boroes</hi> of the ſaid word <hi>Borhes, Pledges</hi> or <hi>Suerties:</hi> albeit in the weſterne parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme they be commonly named <hi>Tythings,</hi> bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they conteine (as I told you) the number of ten men with their families. And euen as ten times ten do make an hundred, ſo, bicauſe it was then alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that tenne of theſe companies ſhould at certeine times méete togither for their matters of greater waight, therefore that generall aſſemblie (or court) was (and yet is) called a <hi>Hundred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, it was then alſo ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that if any man were of ſo euil cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that he could not get himſelfe to be receiued into one of theſe <hi>Tythings</hi> or <hi>Boroes,</hi> that then he ſhould be ſhut vp in priſon, as a man vnwoorthie to liue at libertie amongſt men abroad.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">Tything man. Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>8</hi> Now whereas euery of theſe <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things</hi> (or <hi>Boroes</hi>) did vſe to make choiſe of one man among themſelues, to ſpeak and do in the name of them all: he was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27340:5"/>
therefore in ſome places called the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingman,</hi> in other places the <hi>Boroes Ealder</hi> (whom we now cal <hi>Borſholder</hi>) in other places the <hi>Boroehead,</hi> or <hi>Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroe,</hi> &amp; in ſome other places the <hi>Chiefe pledge,</hi> which laſt name doth plainelie expound the other thrée that are next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: for <hi>Head</hi> or elder of the <hi>Boroes,</hi> &amp; chiefe of the <hi>Pledges</hi> be all one. And in ſome ſhires, where euerie third borrow hath a <hi>Conſtable,</hi> there the officers of the other two be called <hi>Thirdboroes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin">49. E. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. Kanc.</note>
               <hi>9</hi> Moreouer, in theſe <hi>Tythings</hi> (or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes) ſundry good orders were obſerued,<note place="margin">Old or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in Tithings</note> and amongſt others theſe: firſt that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man at the age of 12. yéeres ſhuld be ſworne to the <hi>King:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. 45, Ed. 3.27 Et Kitc. Fol. 12.</note> then, that no man ſhould be ſuffered to dwell in anie towne or place, vnleſſe he were alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into ſome ſuch ſuertieſhip and pledge as is aforeſaid. Thirdly, that if anie of theſe pledges were impriſoned for his offence, that then he ought not to be deliuered without the aſſent of the reſt of his pledges: againe, that no man might remoue out of one <hi>Tything</hi> (or <hi>Boroe</hi>) to dwell in another, without lawful warrant in that behalfe: laſtly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27340:6"/>
that euerie of theſe pledges ſhould yéer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be preſented and brought foorth, by their chiefe pledge at a generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie for that purpoſe, which we yet (in remembrance thereof) do call the <hi>View</hi> of <hi>Franke pledge,</hi> or the <hi>Leete</hi> court.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Hitherto haue I opened the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent office of the <hi>Borſholder, Tything<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and the reſt, whereof alſo there is yet to this day ſome ſhew or remnant in our <hi>Leetes</hi> or <hi>Lawdaies:</hi> but if the verie ſubſtance thereof were thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed (as I knowe no let, but that by law it may) then ſhuld the peace of the land be much better maintained.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His later office.</note>As touching the later office that theſe <hi>Borſholders,</hi> Tythingmen, Headboroes Boroeheads, Thirdboroes, and chiefe pledges haue, it is in manner all one with the office of a <hi>Conſtable</hi> of a towne or pariſh, which is commonlie named a <hi>Petie Conſtable,</hi> or Vndercon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, bicauſe he is a ſmall Conſtable, in reſpect of the Conſtable of his <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,</hi> within whoſe limit he is. For, as about the beginning of the reigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, petie Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles were deuiſed in townes &amp; pariſhes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27340:6"/>
for the aide of the Conſtables of the <hi>Hundreds:</hi> ſo of latter times alſo, <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholders, Tythingmen, Headborroes,</hi> and ſuch like, haue béene vſed as petie Conſtables within their owne Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and Tythings. And yet not ſo vniuerſally, but that ſome of them haue at this daie none other but their olde office. For in ſome of the Weſterne parts of <hi>Englande,</hi> you ſhall ſée, that where there be many <hi>Tythingmen</hi> in one pariſh, there onelie one of them is a <hi>Conſtable</hi> for the <hi>Queene,</hi> and the reſt doe ſerue but as the ancient <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingmen</hi> did. Now therefore, hauing ſpoken of the names and beginnings of theſe inferiour officers of the peace, let vs alſo come to the parts of their duties.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Forſomuch as a great and chiefe part of the duty both of theſe <hi>High</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables of Lathes, Rapes,<note place="margin">Diuiſion of their office.</note> Wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, Hundreds, and Franchiſes, and alſo of theſe <hi>Conſtables,</hi> Petie conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Tythingmen, Borſholders, Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowheads, Headborrowes, Thirdbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, chiefe pledges, &amp; ſuch like mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, by whatſoeuer other names they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27340:7"/>
be called in anie Townes, Pariſhes, Tythings, Borrowes, Hamlets, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of the Realme, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the maintenance of the <hi>Queenes Maieſties</hi> peace, wherin (as alſo in ſom other points) the power of them all is alike, and but one, within their ſeuerall limits and places of authoritie: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thinke it good to ſhew, firſt what their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and equall dutie is in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the peace, either by their owne authoritie, or vnder the authoritie of others: then afterwarde to declare, what their common and like dutie is in ſome other things, not concerning the Peace: and laſtly, to open thoſe things wherein they haue a diſtinct and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dutie one from another.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">Their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the peace.</note>
               <hi>12</hi> The Conſeruation (or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) of the Peace, ſtandeth in thrée things, that is to ſaie, firſt in foreſéeing that nothing be done that tendeth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directlie, or by meanes, to the breach of the peace: ſecondlie, in quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or pacifieng thoſe that are occupied in the breach of the peace: and thirdlie, in puniſhing ſuch as haue alreadie bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the peace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:27340:7"/>And here leaſt anie man ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in not vnderſtanding what is ment by theſe words.<note place="margin">What is the breach of the peace.</note> 
               <hi>The breach of the peace,</hi> he muſt firſt of all know, that by the breach of the peace, is vnderſtood, not onlie that fighting which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie cal the breach of the peace, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that euery murder, rape, manſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and felonie, whatſoeuer, and euerie affraieng, (or putting in feare) of the <hi>Queenes</hi> people, whether it be by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull wearing of armour, or by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of people to do anie vnlawful act, are taken to be diſturbances or <hi>brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> of the peace.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <note place="margin">13. H. 7.10. Cur.</note>
               <hi>13</hi> But now,<note place="margin">To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent things againſt the peace.</note> for the better preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that nothing be done againſt the peace, anie of theſe officers aforeſaide may take (or arreſt) ſuſpected perſons, which walke in the night, and ſléepe in the day: or which do haunt anie houſe, where is ſuſpicion of bauderie: &amp; they may carrie them before a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the peace, to find ſuerties of their good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. And if anie ſuch officer be not of ſufficient ſtrength to do that alone,<note place="margin">Fitz in Iuſt. Del <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.171.</note> then may he take méet aid of his neighbours thereto: and they, in ſuch caſes, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellable
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27340:8"/>
to helpe and aſſiſt him.</p>
            <p>Anie of theſe officers may alſo arreſt ſuch ſtrange perſons as doe walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the night ſeaſon: and for that cauſe the ſaid ſtatute of <hi>VVinchester</hi> did ordaine,<note place="margin">13. Ed. 1</note> that night watches ſhoulde be kept yéerelie, from the feaſt of the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion</hi> vntill <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> by ſix men at euerie gate of euerie citie, by twelue men in euerie <hi>Borough</hi> towne, and in euerie other towne by ſix men, or foure men, or according to the number of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants in the towne, all the night long from Sunne ſetting to Sunne ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: ſo that if anie ſtranger did paſſe, he ſhould be arreſted till the morning, and then for at large (if no ſuſpicion were found of him) but if anie ſuſpicion fell out againſt him, then he ſhuld be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned till he might be lawfully deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And of theſe watches, the officers before named haue the charge within the limits (or places) of their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as the <hi>Conſtable</hi> in his towne, the <hi>Borſholder</hi> in his Boroe, and the high <hi>Conſtable</hi> within al his <hi>Hundred:</hi> and theſe officers ought to ſée theſe <hi>Watches</hi> duelie ſet and kept, and ought alſo to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27340:8"/>
cauſe <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Crie</hi> to be raiſed after ſuch as will not obey the arreſt of ſuch watchmen.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. Nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Ed. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 3.</note>Againe, if anie perſon whatſoeuer (except the <hi>Queenes</hi> ſeruants and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in hir preſence, or in executing hir precepts, or their offices, or ſuch as ſhall aſſiſt them: and except it be vpon <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Crie</hi> made to kéepe the peace, and that in places where actes againſt the Peace doe happen) ſhall be ſo bolde, as to go, or ride armed, by night, or by day, in Faires, Markets, or anie other places: then any <hi>Conſtable</hi> or any other of the ſaide <hi>Officers,</hi> may take ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour from him, for the <hi>Queenes</hi> vſe, and may alſo commit him to the <hi>Gaole.</hi> And therefore, it ſhall be good in this behalfe, for theſe officers to ſtaie and arteſt all ſuch perſons as they ſhall find to carrie <hi>Dags,</hi> or <hi>Piſtols,</hi> or to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled with priuie coates, or dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. Eliz. Reg.</note> as by the Proclamation (made in the one and twentieth yéere of the reigne of our <hi>Souereigne Ladie</hi> that now is) they are ſpecially commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">17 R. 2. c. 8.</note>Furthermore, if anie great aſſembly,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27340:9"/>
or rumor of people be made in manner of inſurrection, then the <hi>Shiriffes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables,</hi> and the ſaid other miniſters, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge thereof, ought to go with the ſtrength of the countie, and to ſet themſelues againſt it, and ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to take and impriſon ſuch offendors.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Bar. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 22. Ed. 35. Bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> if any man do threaten to kill another, and he which is ſo threatened do praie anie of theſe <hi>Officers</hi> to arreſt the other to find ſuerties of the <hi>Peace,</hi> then may ſuch an officer arreſt him to finde ſuch ſuertie before a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the Peace, and may alſo carrie him to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon if he refuſe to find it.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <note place="margin">To paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the breach of the peace.</note>
               <hi>14</hi> Thus much I haue ſpoken of thoſe things which doe bend towardes the breach of the peace:<note place="margin">1. H. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> but now I will come nearer, to the breach it ſelfe, and withall to the pacifieng and puniſhing of the ſame.</p>
            <p>If therefore a <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaide officers, ſhall ſée anie men going about to breake the peace, as by vſing hot words, by which an <hi>Affray</hi> is like to grow, then ought ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> to command thoſe perſons to auoid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of impriſonment: and if they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27340:9"/>
will not depart, but ſhal draw weapon, or giue anie blowe, then ought he to doe his beſt to depart them, &amp; to kéepe them in ſunder: and he may (for that purpoſe) both vſe his owne weapon,<note place="margin">3. H. 7. cap. 10.21. H. 7. cap. 21.</note> and may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo call others to aſſiſt him. In which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if any ſuch officer, or other perſon comming on his part, doe take hurt, he ſhal haue good remedie by action againſt him that did the hurt: but if anie of them that made the <hi>Affraie,</hi> be hurt by ſuch officer, or by any of his companie, then ſuch a hurt perſon hath no remedie at all for it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">13. E. 4. cap. 9.</note>And if he that maketh an <hi>Affray</hi> doe flie into an houſe, when ſuch an officer commeth to arreſt him: then may that officer breake open the doores to take him: and if he that made the <hi>Affray</hi> do flie from thence alſo, yet may the <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> followe him, and in freſh ſuite take him, though it be in another <hi>Shire</hi> or Countie.</p>
            <p>So, if two men be fighting togither in a houſe (the doores being ſhut) yet may ſuch an <hi>Officer</hi> breake open the doores to cauſe the peace to be kept, though none of the parties haue taken hurt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27340:10"/>
And in both theſe cauſes, ſuch an officer may carrie them before a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the peace to finde <hi>Suertie</hi> for the peace, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue broken the peace alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and are méete to be bound that they ſhall not thenceforth breake it againe.</p>
            <p>But if any of the parties to an <hi>Affray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fitz. 72.38. Ed. 3 6. &amp; 22. li. Aſ. 56.</note> haue receiued any dangerous hurt, then ought ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> to arreſt him that did the hurt, and to carry him to the <hi>Gaole,</hi> there to remaine till he find ſuertie to appéere at the next <hi>Gaole</hi> deliuerie: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he may with leſſe labour car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie him to a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the peace, who ought to take order for ſuch ſuertie, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the fact may fall out to be <hi>Felonie,</hi> if ſo be that he which was hurt doe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to die within one yéere and a day next following ſuch hurt done.</p>
            <p>And as theſe <hi>Officers</hi> ought to are reſt thoſe that doe make <hi>Aſſault</hi> vppon any priuate perſons,<note place="margin">5. H. 7.</note> ſo alſo may they arreſt any ſuch as ſhall make aſſault (or <hi>Affray</hi>) vpon themſelues whileſt they be in doing their offices: and may for that purpoſe both lawfully defende themſelues, and alſo take the offendors and commit them to the <hi>Gaole,</hi> or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27340:10"/>
them to a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the peace, for the finding of ſuch ſuertie as is aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Barr. 101 en Fitz.</note>But if one do aſſalt a man, in, or nigh the high way, to rob him, and be taken by the true man, or by any other, and be brought to the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other <hi>Officer</hi> of the place: then ought ſuch <hi>Officer,</hi> not onelie to take him to his warde, but alſo to carrie him before a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace to cauſe him to giue ſuertie for his <hi>Good abearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ed. 3. cap. 14.17. E 4. cap. 5.</note>So, if any man do ſuſpect another of <hi>Murder,</hi> or <hi>Felonie,</hi> and doe declare the ſame to any ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> of the place, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch officer may arreſt the ſuſpected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and he ſhall doe well to carrie him to a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the Peace togither with him that doth ſuſpect him, to that end that they both may be examined as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth. Yea, any of the ſaid officers may ſearch within the limit of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ed. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 9.</note> for any perſons ſuſpected of <hi>Felonie:</hi> for it is a chieſe part of their office to repreſſe felons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note>And therefore any of theſe <hi>Officers</hi> may (of his owne authoritie) arreſt one that is indited of <hi>Felonie:</hi> So, if the common voice and fame be, that <hi>A. B.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:27340:11"/>
hath done a felonie, that is ſufficient cauſe for any of theſe <hi>Officers</hi> (that ſhall thereof ſuſpect him) to arreſt him for it.</p>
            <p>And I like well of their opinion which doe holde,<note place="margin">1. H. 7.7</note> that if information be giuen to any ſuch Officer, that a man and a woman be in adulterie, or forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation togither, then the Officer may take companie with him, and that if he find them ſo, he may carrie them to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>But this is to be marked,<note place="margin">3. H. 4.22. E 4 cap. 35.</note> that in the caſes before, and ſuch like, where ſuch an <hi>Officer</hi> hath arreſted, or hath in his ward any offendor that ought to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the gaole, there ſuch an Officer is not bound foorthwith to carrie him, but may wel for a reaſonable time kéepe him in the <hi>Stocks,</hi> vntill that conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent prouiſion of ſtrength may be made to conuey him ſafely thither.<note place="margin">4. Ed. cap. 10</note> And when he ſhall bring ſuch offendor to the gaole, then ought the <hi>Gaoler</hi> to receiue the ſame fréely, without taking any thing of the <hi>Officer</hi> for it.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <note place="margin">Seruing of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</note>
               <hi>15</hi> Hitherto (as you ſée) I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> and of theſe other <hi>Officers,</hi> ſo farre onely as they haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27340:11"/>
by their owne offices, without any commandement from others. But forſomuch as a great part of their dutie (concerning the peace) reſteth in the making of due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the precepts of <hi>Higher</hi> officers, and ſpecially of the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the peace, who be (as it were) immediately ſet ouer them, let vs alſo ſée after what maner theſe <hi>Conſtables,</hi> and other the ſaide inferiour miniſters of the Peace, ought to behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Albeit then, that theſe ſaid <hi>Officers</hi> be ſubiect to the commandements of the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of gaole deliuerie, and of <hi>Oier</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and of ſome <hi>Higher Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,</hi> yea, and to the precepts of <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> alſo, and of other <hi>Officers,</hi> in ſome certeine caſes, yet bicauſe moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are called vpon by the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. 8. p. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. 7. p. 22.</note> they ought ſpecially to ſhewe themſelues obedient to their precepts, and may not diſpute whether their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements be grounded vpon ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent authoritie, or no: as knowing that although a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the Peace (which is a Iudge of <hi>Record</hi>) ſhoulde direct a <hi>Warrant</hi> beyonde his authoritie to a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27340:12"/>
               <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or one other of the ſaide <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> yet ſhall ſuch Officer be holden excuſed for executing the ſame, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace himſelfe bée blamed for it.</p>
            <p>If therfore a <hi>Warrant</hi> for the Peace, or good abearing, happen to be directed to any of theſe ſaid <hi>Officers,</hi> then ought he with all ſpéede and ſecrecie to finde out the partie: and then alſo may hée laie his hands vpon him, and ſhew him the matter, and require him in the <hi>Queenes</hi> name to go with him to put in ſuertie according to the <hi>Warrant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21. H. cap. 3</note> And this if the partie ſhall refuſe to doe, then ought ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> foorthwith to arreſt him, and to conueye him to priſon, without carrieng him to any <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> in which doing, if the partie ſhall offer any reſiſtance, or ſhall ſeeke to eſcape, then alſo may ſuch Officer iuſtifie the beating, or the hurting of him.</p>
            <p>But if the partie ſhall yéeld to go and giue <hi>Suertie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21. H cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and yet will not go to ſuch <hi>Iuſtice</hi> as made out the <hi>Warrant,</hi> but to ſome other <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> then ought ſuch officer to giue him that libertie, ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27340:12"/>
that it be not far out of the <hi>Limit,</hi> for elſe ſo great trauell might folowe vpon the Officer, as rather he than the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor might ſéeme to be puniſhed by it.</p>
            <p>And here the <hi>Officer</hi> muſt take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and conſider whether the <hi>Warrant</hi> doe come directly from the méere autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, or elſe be grounded vppon a writ of <hi>Supplicauit</hi> ſent downe from higher authoritie (which difference ought to appéere plainely in all <hi>Warrants</hi> that be well and orderlie made.) And if the <hi>Warrant</hi> be grounded vppon ſuch a Writ, then may ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> compell the partie to go to the very ſame <hi>Iuſtice</hi> or <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace that made out the <hi>warrant,</hi> and otherwiſe he may carrie him to priſon, as is ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Neither is it requiſite, that ſuch an <hi>Officer</hi> ſhould danſe vp and downe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the partie (as many vſe to doe) vntil he can finde out ſuerties: but he may lawfullie kéepe him, vntill that he can get ſuerties to come vnto him: the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of which point is the cauſe, both that many an euill man eſcapeth, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie an honeſt Officer is puniſhed for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:27340:13"/>But here it happeneth many times, that the purtie (hearing that the peace is granted againſt him) offereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with ſuerties, for that cauſe vnto ſome other <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace, or findeth ſuch ſuertie in ſome of the Courts at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and ſo hath a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> ready to ſhew ſuch <hi>Officer,</hi> as commeth to him with a <hi>Warrant</hi> as is aforeſaide. Now, if that be ſo, then is the <hi>Officer</hi> diſcharged thereby, and ought not any further to moleſt the partie. But yet it ſhall be good, that ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> doe kéepe the <hi>Superſedeas</hi> for his better diſcharge: leaſt otherwiſe he be called to account for not ſeruing the <hi>Warrant</hi> that was ſent vnto him.</p>
            <p>If a <hi>Warrant</hi> be directed to a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,</hi> or ſuch other <hi>Officer,</hi> to arreſt our that is indited of <hi>Felonie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22. lib. Aſſ 55. Cor. 261 288.318 en Fitz.</note> then may ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> iuſtifie the killing of ſuch a partie, if it ſo be, that he cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take him: or of ſo be, that he reſiſt, or flie, when he is taken.</p>
            <p>Finally, the <hi>Conſtable</hi> or ſuch other of the ſaid <hi>Officers,</hi> hauing arreſted any to be conueied ſo the Gaole, muſt take good héed, that he doe not willingly, or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27340:13"/>
negligently, ſuffer ſuch partie to eſcape from him. For, if the arreſt were for <hi>Felonie,</hi> then by a willing eſcape the <hi>Officer</hi> himſelfe becommeth a <hi>Felon</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And of whatſoeuer other kinde the offence be, if the <hi>Officer</hi> do, by his will, or negligence, ſuffer the partie to eſcape from him, he ſhall be fined for it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quantitie of his fault, by the diſcretion of thoſe that ſhall be <hi>Iudges</hi> of it. And leaſt any ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> ſhoulde flatter himſelf, in thinking that he may paſſe through with ſome eaſie <hi>Fine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. H. 4. cap. 12. Stan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 35</note> I let him knowe, that the <hi>Iudges</hi> of his fault may ſet his fine, equall with the value of all his goods, if in their diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the ſame doe ſo require.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16</hi> Thus haue I performed the firſt part of my promiſe, and haue ſhewed,<note place="margin">The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe Officers, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> what is the equall and like dutie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of the ſaide <hi>Officers</hi> in matters concerning the <hi>Peace,</hi> both by their owne authoritie, and alſo in dooing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of peace: now therfore I muſt go forward to the ſecond part of my purpoſe, and am to declare their like dutie in other points of ſeruice, that doe not concerne the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27340:14"/>
               <hi>Peace.</hi> For equal power is indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen to any of theſe <hi>Officers</hi> by ſom <hi>Statutes</hi> of the realme, whereof theſe that follow be the chiefe.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <note place="margin">Attenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of ſtatutes.</note>
               <hi>17</hi> All <hi>Conſtables</hi> and other the ſaid <hi>Officers</hi> ought to be attendant, aiding,<note place="margin">33. H. 8. ca. 10 &amp; 37. H. 8. cap. 7.</note> and aſſiſting to the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, for the execution of all and euerie the acts (made in, or before the <hi>Parleament,</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the <hi>33.</hi> yéere of the reigne of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight) concerning <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinors,</hi> giuing of <hi>Liueries, Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Embracerie, Boweſtaues, Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Vnlawfull games, Foreſtallers, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grators, Vittaile, Vittailers, and Inhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> or any of them, vppon paine that the ſaid <hi>Conſtables,</hi> and other the ſaide <hi>Officers</hi> ſhall make ſuch <hi>Fines,</hi> as by two of the ſaid <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace ſhal be aſſeſſed.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <note place="margin">Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note>
               <hi>18</hi> All <hi>Conſtables,</hi> and other the ſaide <hi>Officers</hi> within <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14. H 8. cap. 5. 32. H 8. cap. 2.1. M. Pa. 1. cap. 9.</note> or within ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen miles thereof, ought (vpon requeſt made, to aide and aſſiſt the <hi>Preſident of</hi> the <hi>Colledge</hi> of the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and other perſons authorized for the due execution of the Statutes made concerning <hi>Phyſicians, Apothecaries,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:27340:14"/>
and <hi>Surgeons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">
               <note place="margin">23. H. 6. cap. 14.</note>
               <hi>19</hi> If any perſon ſhall (without law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bargaine) puruey or take any thing of any of the <hi>Queenes</hi> liege people,<note place="margin">Puruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors.</note> to the vſe of any (other than of the <hi>Queene</hi> and hir houſe) and thereof notice be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer</hi> of the place, then ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> ought (vnder the paine of twentie pound) to arreſt ſuch taker, and to carrie him to the next priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">28. H. 6. ſta. 2 c. 2</note>No Purueior of the <hi>Queene</hi> ought to take any horſe, or cart, but by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie of the <hi>Maior, Bailife, Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other officer of the place whence that taking ſhall be.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">25. Ed. 3 cap. 1. 36. Ed. 3 ſta. 2 c. 2</note>Corne ought to be taken for the <hi>Queenes</hi> houſe, by ſtriked meaſure of eight buſhels to the quarter, according as is vſed throughout the land: and the takers of all things to be taken for the <hi>Queenes</hi> houſe, ſhall make their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiance by the verie values thereof, by the viewe of the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or other ſuch <hi>Officer,</hi> and by appraiſement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der oth of foure other good men of the towne, where the taking ſhall be: and ſuch taking ſhall be made without dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27340:15"/>
the preiſors by compaſſion, mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or other villanie, to ſet any other price than their oth will, and as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly runneth in the next <hi>Markets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Takers, Vndertakers,<note place="margin">2 &amp; 3. P &amp; Mar. cap. 6.</note> their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or ſeruants, ſhall not take any Beefes, Weathers, Lambes, Calues, or any kinde of Saltfiſh, or any kinde of graine, or any Butter in any veſſels, or Cheeſe, Bacon, Conies, Pigs, Geeſe, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, or Hens, but by <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and a <hi>Blanke</hi> thereto for that ſhire annexed: in which <hi>Blanke,</hi> the ſaid ſeueral things ſo to be taken, &amp; the priſes of them ſhall be written, &amp; to which <hi>Blanke,</hi> the <hi>High Conſtable, Pety Conſtable,</hi> or <hi>Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> of the place which any ſuch taking ſhall be, ought to ſubſcribe his name or ſigne manuell. And ſuch Taker ought then alſo to make a <hi>Briefe</hi> or <hi>Docket</hi> in writing ſubſcribed with his name, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining euerie of the ſaide things ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in euerie place: and ought then alſo (vnder the paine of a Hundred Marks) to deliuer the ſame to the ſaide <hi>High Conſtable, Petie Conſtable,</hi> or <hi>Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> who alſo ought to deliuer it ouer to the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace at their next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27340:15"/>
               <hi>Seſſions</hi> within that countie.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <note place="margin">10. Ed. 3 cap. 1.</note>
               <hi>20</hi> In the takings for the <hi>Queenes</hi> houſe, <hi>Tailes</hi> (or Indentures) ought to be made and ſealed, betwéene the taker and the owner (in the preſence of the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other officer, and the preiſors of the place) by which <hi>Tailes</hi> (or Indentures) ſatiſfaction ought to be made to the owner for his things ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <note place="margin">20. H. 6. cap. 8.</note>
               <hi>21</hi> If any Taker will make puruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of any thing (not excéeding the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of xl. s.) and make not readie pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in hand therefore, it is lawfull for the owner to reteine the thing ſo taken, and to reſiſt ſuch purueiance: and the <hi>Conſtable, Tythingma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or <hi>chiefe pledge</hi> of the place (being thereto required by the owner) ought to aide and aſſiſt ſuch owner in making ſuch reſiſtance, vnder paine to yéeld vnto him the value of the thing taken, &amp; his double dammages.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <note place="margin">14. Eliz. cap. 5.</note>
               <hi>22</hi> If the <hi>Conſtable, Tythingman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rogues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> or ſuch other officer, of any place, be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and doe not his beſt indeuour, for the apprehenſion of all ſturdie <hi>Rogues,</hi> or vagabends, that ſhall beg, wander, or miſorder themſelues within his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27340:16"/>
and for the bringing of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace, but ſhall ſuffer any ſuch to eſcape, then ſhall ſuch <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,</hi> or <hi>Officer</hi> forfaite vj. s. viij.d. for euerie ſuch Rogue.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <note place="margin">Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>
               <hi>23</hi> All <hi>Conſtables</hi> and other the ſaid <hi>Officers</hi> muſt be attendant vpon <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21. H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 2.22. H. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. 14.32. H. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. 3.</note> for the abiuring and conueieng of ſuch perſons, as ſhal take the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard as a <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi> for ſafegarde of their liues, by occaſion of any <hi>Felonie</hi> by them done.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22</hi> All theſe things heretofore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed, whether they concerne the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the <hi>Peace,</hi> or any other matter beſides the Peace, may &amp; ought to be done and executed indifferently (as I thinke) by any of the ſaide <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> within the precinct of his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: that is to ſay, as well by the high <hi>Conſtable</hi> of the whole <hi>Hundred</hi> or Franchiſe, within his <hi>Hundred</hi> or fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, as by the <hi>Conſtable, pety Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Tythingman, Borſholder, Boroe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, Headboroe, Thirdboroe,</hi> or <hi>chiefe Pledge,</hi> within his towne, pariſh, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Boroe, or Hamlet: and that ſo, as none of them hath more power of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27340:16"/>
therin than the other, although ſome of them haue longer limits of place tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt.</p>
            <p>But now I am come to ſuch things as do ſeuerally belong to ſome of theſe <hi>Officers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">High Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a Hundred.</note> ſo as the others may not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle therewith (which is the third part of my promiſe) and therefore I will take that in hand alſo: and bicauſe the <hi>Conſtable</hi> of the Hundred, or franchiſe, is the greateſt of theſe Officers, both in reſpect of his larger precinct of place, and alſo of the higher truſt that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him, I will begin at him: who, as he is not by and by ſet alone, but is for ſome matters no further au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized than ſome other of the ſaid <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> ſo I will firſt begin at thoſe, and then come to the reſt that belong onelie to himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <note place="margin">14. Eliz. cap. 5.</note>
               <hi>25</hi> The mony appointed to be leuied by the <hi>Churchwardens</hi> of euerie pariſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth <hi>Sonday</hi> for the reliefe of Priſoners in the Gaole,<note place="margin">Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> ought (vnder the paine of fiue <abbr>l</abbr>.) to be paied by them once euerie quarter of a yéer to the high <hi>Conſtables</hi> or head <hi>Officers</hi> of euery Hundred, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Wapentake, towne, or pariſh:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27340:17"/>
and the ſaide high <hi>Conſtables,</hi> or head <hi>Officers</hi> ought (vnder the paine of <hi>5.</hi> 
               <abbr>l</abbr>.) to paie ouer the ſame money ſo to them paid, of the next quarter <hi>Seſſions</hi> of the Peace, to ſuch perſon as ſhal be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace to receiue the ſame.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <note place="margin">Collec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or for the poore.</note>
               <hi>26</hi> If any perſon lawfully appointed by the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace to be Collector for the poore, ſhall refuſe to accept it,<note place="margin">14. El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 5.</note> or accepting it, ſhall be negligent therein, he ſhal loſe to the poore of that place for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhillings, which ſhall be leuied by <hi>diſtreſſe,</hi> or recouerie by <hi>Action</hi> by the high <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or <hi>Tythingman</hi> of the place: who alſo, if he be negligent, or refuſe ſo to ſue within two monethes next after ſuch default, ſhall loſe fiue pounds.</p>
            <p>It ſéemeth to me, that in theſe two ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes next aboue, the words, high <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> high <hi>Tythingmen,</hi> &amp; head <hi>Officers</hi> doe exclude <hi>Petie Conſtables, Borſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and ſuch like to meddle therein: bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none are called <hi>High,</hi> or <hi>Head,</hi> but in compariſon of <hi>Lowe</hi> and <hi>Baſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">High Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alone.</note> Now therefore I will ſpeake of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the high <hi>Conſtable</hi> of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27340:17"/>
the hundred alone.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <note place="margin">5. Eliz. cap. 4.</note>
               <hi>27 High Conſtables</hi> of Hundreds in all ſuch <hi>Shires,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pety ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> where <hi>Petie Seſſions</hi> for ſeruants and labourers (otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſtatute Seſſions) were vſed to be kept, before the firſt day of the Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament holden in the fift yéere of the reigne of our gracious <hi>Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> may yet ſtill holde their ſaid <hi>Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ſo that nothing be done in them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the <hi>Statute</hi> of labourers and ſeruants made in the ſame <hi>Parlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">
               <note place="margin">13. E. 1. ſta. Wy.</note>
               <hi>28</hi> The <hi>Conſtables</hi> of Hundreds,<note place="margin">Watches and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies.</note> and of Franchiſes, ought to make preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, and to all other <hi>Iuſtices</hi> thereto aſſigned, of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults of watches, and of the defaults of the <hi>Queenes</hi> highwaies not inlarged ſo, as no ditches, vnderwood, or buſhes be within <hi>200.</hi> foote on euerie ſide of the ſame, and alſo of ſuch as lodge ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in vplandiſh townes, for whome they will not anſwere.</p>
            <p n="29">
               <note place="margin">14. Eli. cap. 5.</note>
               <hi>29</hi> The <hi>Conſtables,</hi> or <hi>Tythingmen</hi> of euerie Hundred, Rape,<note place="margin">Poore people.</note> or Wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, in which any abiding place to ſet the poore people in, ſhall be appointed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27340:18"/>
by the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, ſhall once eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie moneth (vnder the paine of twentis ſhillings) make a view and ſearch of all the aged, impotent, and lame perſons within their authoritie, and all ſuch as they ſhall finde, not being borne, nor within thrée yéers next before dwelling within that diuiſion (except lepreus and Bedread perſons) they ſhall preſentlie ſée conueied, on horſebacke, in cart, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe by their diſcreations, to the next <hi>Conſtable,</hi> and ſo from <hi>Conſtable</hi> to <hi>Conſtable,</hi> the directeſt way, till eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of them be brought to the place where he or ſhe was borne, or moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant by the ſpace of thrée yéeres next before, there to remaine in ſome ſuch abiding place, or otherwiſe to be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for.</p>
            <p n="30">
               <note place="margin">High waies.</note>
               <hi>30 Eſtreates</hi> indented ought to bée made by the <hi>Clearks</hi> of the Peace,<note place="margin">2. &amp; 3. P &amp; Mar. cap. 8 &amp; 5. El. 13.</note> and by <hi>Stewards</hi> of <hi>Leetes,</hi> of all forfaitures riſing in the <hi>Seſſions</hi> of the Peace, or in <hi>Leetes,</hi> vppon the Statutes of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies: of which <hi>Eſtreats,</hi> one part ought to bée deliuered yéerelie within ſixe wéekes after <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> to the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life or high <hi>Conſtable</hi> of the Hundred,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27340:18"/>
Lathe, or Wapentake, wherein the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault was committed, and the other part to the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> of the pariſh in which the default was made, to the inſent, that ſuch <hi>Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life,</hi> or <hi>chiefe Conſtable,</hi> may thereby leuie by diſtreſſe the ſame forfaitures, or the double thereof (if no diſtreſſe can be found, or if ſuch forfaitures be not paid within twentie daies after a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full demand of the ſame by the ſaid offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer) and to the intent alſo that the ſaide <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Churchwardens</hi> of the pariſh may therby cal the ſaid <hi>Bailife,</hi> or <hi>High Conſtable</hi> to account before two <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the Peace (the one being of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) betwéene the firſt day of <hi>March,</hi> and the laſt of <hi>Aprill</hi> yéerely for the ſaid forfaitures, which ought by the ſaid <hi>Churchwardens</hi> to be beſtowed on the <hi>Highwaies</hi> in their pariſh. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch account, euerie ſuch <hi>Bailife,</hi> or <hi>high Conſtable</hi> ſhall haue for his paines viii. pence of euerie pound leuied and paied by him, and may alſo reteine xij. pence for the fée of the <hi>Clearke</hi> of the Peace or Steward of the <hi>Leete,</hi> for euerie ſuch <hi>Eſtreate</hi> by any of them deliuered, as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27340:19"/>
is aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="31">
               <note place="margin">Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a towne.</note>
               <hi>31</hi> Next after the <hi>Conſtable</hi> of the Hundred, Wapentake, or Franchiſe, followeth the <hi>Conſtable</hi> of a Towne, who is ſomewhere called a <hi>High Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,</hi> for that he hath there a <hi>Petie Conſtable</hi> vnder him, and is ſomtimes alſo termed a <hi>Head Officer,</hi> bicauſe in ſome Corporate townes <hi>Conſtable</hi> is part of the name of their <hi>Incorporation.</hi> And now alſo bicauſe there be ſundrie things that are by the <hi>Statute</hi> Lawes indifferently referred to him, or to the <hi>Tythingman, Borſholder,</hi> or ſuch other inferiour officer of the place: therefore I will firſt ſet downe thoſe, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſpeake of the reſt that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him only, and to none of them.</p>
            <p n="32">
               <note place="margin">Serua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note>
               <hi>32</hi> No perſon reteined in huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie,<note place="margin">5. Eliz. cap. 4.</note> or in any the Arts appointed by the Statute of <hi>Labourers</hi> (made in the fift yéere of our Souereigne Ladie <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi>) may depart, after the time of ſuch reteinour expired, out of the towne or pariſh where he laſt ſerued, to ſerue in another, vnleſſe he haue a <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall</hi> vnder the ſeale of the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or other ſuch <hi>Officer,</hi> and of two other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27340:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
houſholders of the towne or pariſh where he laſt ſerued, according to this forme: <hi>Memorandum, <hi>that A.B. late ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of C.D. of E. in the countie of K. husbandman, or Tailor, &amp;c. is licenſed to depart from his ſaide Maiſter, and is at his libertie to ſerue elſewhere, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtatute in that caſe made and prouided. In witneſſe whereof, &amp;c. dated the day, moneth, yeere, and place of the making thereof.</hi>
               </hi> Which <hi>Teſtimoniall,</hi> the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh where ſuch Maiſter, Miſtreſſe, or Dame doth dwell, ought to regiſter, taking onelie ij.d. therefore. And if ſuch perſon be accepted into any other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, without ſhewing ſuch <hi>Teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> to the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> Curate, or Churchwarden of the place where he ſhall be accepted, he ſhall be impriſoned till he procure ſuch a <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimoniall,</hi> which if he doe not within <hi>21.</hi> daies next after the firſt day of his impriſonment, he ſhall be whipped as a <hi>Vagabond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">
               <note place="margin">5. Eliz. cap. 4.</note>
               <hi>33</hi> In the time of hay,<note place="margin">Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note> or cornehar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> of any townſhip, vpon requeſt made,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27340:20"/>
and for auoiding the loſſe of any corne, graine, or haie, may cauſe all ſuch artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and perſons (as be meet to labour) by his diſcretion to ſerue by the day, for the mowing, reaping, ſhearing, getting, or inning of corne, graine, or hay, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſkill and qualitie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and if any ſuch perſon ſhall refuſe ſo to do, then ought ſuch <hi>Officer</hi> (vnder the paine of fortie ſhillings) to impriſon ſuch refuſer in the <hi>Stocks,</hi> by the ſpace of two daies and one night.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <note place="margin">Rogue.</note>
               <hi>34</hi> Euerie <hi>Rogue</hi> that ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended,<note place="margin">18. Eliz cap. 3.</note> ought to be conueied (from the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace before whome he ſhall be brought) by the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or ſuch other Officer of the pariſh where the apprehenſion ſhall be, but onelie to the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> Tythingman, or other ſuch Officer of the next Towneſhip, or pariſh, in the next Hundred, and ſo from one Hundred to another, by the <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> or ſuch other <hi>Officer</hi> of euerie ſuch Towneſhip or pariſh which ſhalbe next in euery ſuch Hundred, the direct waie, vntil they ſhal come to the <hi>Gaole</hi> or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon appointed for ſuch <hi>Rogues:</hi> vnder the paine of vj. s. viij d. for euery default
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27340:20"/>
of ſuch <hi>Conſtable</hi> or Officer.</p>
            <p n="35">
               <hi>35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The <hi>Conſtable, Borſholder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">High waies.</note> or other ſuch Officer, and the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of euerie pariſh, ought yéerely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Tueſday or Wedneſday in <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter weeke,</hi> to call togither a number of the pariſhioners, and to chooſe two ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men of their pariſh, to be <hi>Suruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors</hi> of the works for amendment of the high waies within their pariſh leading to any market towne: and ought then alſo to appoint ſixe daies for the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe high waies before Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommer then next folowing: and ought openly in the Church, the next Sunday after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> to giue knowledge of the ſame ſixe daies.</p>
            <p>They alſo ought to haue one part of the <hi>Eſtreates</hi> indited, and may call the <hi>Bailife</hi> or high <hi>Conſtable</hi> to <hi>Accompt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. &amp; 3. P &amp; Mar. cap. 8. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. El. 13.</note> concerning the forfaitures for default of amending <hi>Highwaies,</hi> as hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die appéered before. And they alſo or any of them, may leuie by <hi>Diſtreſſe</hi> and by ſale of ſuch <hi>Diſtreſſe,</hi> all ſummes of money forfaited for anye cauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Statute of <hi>Highwaies</hi> made in the eightéenth yéere of the <hi>Queenes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27340:21"/>
Maieſtie</hi> that now is (if ſo be that the <hi>Surueiors</hi> of High waies ſhall not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue leuied and imploied the ſame within one yéere next after the offence committed) &amp; ſhall yéeld <hi>Account</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of before two <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the Peace,<note place="margin">18. Eliz. cap. 10.</note> as is afore ſhewed.</p>
            <p n="36">
               <hi>36</hi> Theſe things laſt aforeſaid, doe (in mine opinion) pertaine as well to the charge of a <hi>Tythingman, Borſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Headboroe,</hi> Chiefe pledge, or ſuch other inferiour Officer of a towne or pariſh, as they doe to the <hi>Conſtable</hi> of ſuch a towne or pariſh,<note place="margin">Things belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging onelie to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.</note> that hath any of thoſe other Officers there vnder him. But ſome other points of charge there be, that belong to him onlie, and to none of them: as for example.</p>
            <p n="37">
               <note place="margin">Weights and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</note>
               <hi>37</hi> Euerie Citie, Borough,<note place="margin">8. H 6. cap. 5. 11. H. 7. cap. 4.</note> and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket towne, that haue a <hi>Conſtable,</hi> ought alſo to haue common meaſures ſealed, and alſo common weights ſealed, at which the inhabitants may fréelye weigh.</p>
            <p n="38">
               <note place="margin">Merchan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dize.</note>
               <hi>38</hi> If any woolles,<note place="margin">14. H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 5.</note> or other merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, be ſhipped to the <hi>Staple,</hi> in any ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected place adioining to the coaſt of the water, then Indentures ought thereof
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27340:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to be made betwéene the owner, and the <hi>Maior</hi> or <hi>Conſtable</hi> of that place: or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſuch merchandize ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faited.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. H. 8. cap. 9.</note>
               <hi>39</hi> The <hi>Maior,</hi> Shirifes, Bailifes,<note place="margin">Vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful games</note> Conſtables, and other head Officers within euerie <hi>Citie,</hi> Borough, &amp; towne within this Realme, where any ſuch Officers be, ought vnder the paine of xl. s. for euerie default, once euerie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at the leaſt, to make ſearch (aſwell within liberties, as without) in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where any vnlawfull games ſhall be ſuſpected to be kept, and may arreſt and impriſon aſwell the kéepers of ſuch places, as the haunters to the ſame, till they be bound, no more to kéepe &amp; haunt ſuch places. And if any ſuch <hi>Head Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> ſhall find or knowe, that any arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, crafteſman, huſbandman, appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, labourer, ſeruant at huſbandrie, iourneyman, or ſeruant of artificer, or that any mariner, fiſherman, waterman or ſeruingman, doth plaie at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, dice, cards, tenniſe, bowles, claſh, coiting, logating, or any other vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full game, out of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> time, or out of their Maiſters houſe or preſence in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27340:22"/>
the <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> time (vnleſſe it be by the licence of ſuch Maiſter as hath <hi>100.</hi> 
               <abbr>l.</abbr> by the yéere, or aboue, and then alſo that plaieng be within the precinct of ſuch Maiſters houſe, garden, or orchard) then ſuch head Officer may commit ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor to warde, till he will be bound by <hi>Obligation</hi> to the <hi>Queenes</hi> vſe (in ſuch ſumme as to the diſcretion of ſuch Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer ſhall be thought reaſonable) that he ſhall not from thencefoorth vſe ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games.</p>
            <p n="40">
               <note place="margin">Bridges.</note>
               <hi>40</hi> Thoſe foure <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace,<note place="margin">22. H. 8. cap. 5.</note> that bée authoriſed by the <hi>Statute</hi> to make taxation of monie for the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any decaied bridge in the high waie, ought to make that taxation, by the aſſent of the <hi>Conſtables,</hi> or of two of the moſt honeſt inhabitants of euerie towne or pariſh.</p>
            <p n="41">
               <note place="margin">Veſſels.</note>
               <hi>41</hi> In all <hi>Cities,</hi> Boroughes,<note place="margin">23. H. 8. cap. 4.</note> and townes, wherein no <hi>Wardens</hi> of <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> be, the <hi>Maiors,</hi> Shirifes, Bailifes, Conſtables, or other head officers there haue power to ſearch, view, and gawge, barrels, kilderkins, firkins, and other veſſels, to be made there, and to take ſuch aduantage thereby, and in ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27340:22"/>
as the Wardens of <hi>Cowpers</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Citie of <hi>London</hi> may take on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie behalfe.</p>
            <p n="42">
               <hi>42</hi> The <hi>Maiors,</hi> Shirifes,<note place="margin">Hats and caps.</note> Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,<note place="margin">21. H. 8. cap. 9. 1. Mar. Parl. 1. cap. 11.</note> and other head Officers of any place, to which woollen hats, bonnets, or caps (being made out of this <hi>Realme</hi>) ſhalbe brought, ought (vpon knowledge thereof to them to be giuen by the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer</hi> of ſuch place, or his deputie) to ioine with ſuch <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> or deputie, in the ſale of ſuch hats, bonnets, or caps for ſuch priſes, as by the ſtatute are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited: vpon paine to forfaite twentie pounds for euerie time that they ſhalbe remiſſe in that ſale.</p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>43</hi> In all theſe caſes alſo, laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed, it ſéemeth that <hi>Borſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Tythingmen, Headboroes,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch (being in townes and pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, vnderneath <hi>Conſtables</hi> that be there) cannot meddle: bicauſe ſuch <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables</hi> be (in compariſon of them) called <hi>Head Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore vpon all the whole diſcourſe before written,<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> it may wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péere, that <hi>Borſholders, Tythingmen, Headboroes, Boroeheads, Thirdboroes,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:27340:23"/>
and chiefe pledges, whether they be there the onelie <hi>Officers</hi> for the peace, or be vnderneth <hi>Conſtables,</hi> may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Borowes, Tythings, or Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, doe manie things that the others may doe: and that there are manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points, which thoſe other <hi>Officers</hi> may doe, and wherewith theſe <hi>Borſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and the reſt cannot meddle at all. And therefore, to auoid idle repetition of matters alreadie ſpoken, I ſay ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it an <hi>Vnder Borſholder, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingman, Headboroe, Boroehead, Thirdboroe,</hi> or chiefe pledge, will ſée what belongeth to him to doe, he muſt looke before vpon all ſuch caſes, where his power is declared to be equall (for thoſe points) with the power, either of a <hi>High Conſtable</hi> of the <hi>Hundred, or a Conſtable</hi> of a towne or pariſh: for in all ſuch things he hath to deale as well as they: but where any thing before is ſhewed to apperteine onlie to the <hi>High Conſtable</hi> of a <hi>Hundred,</hi> or onlie to the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or chiefe or head <hi>Officer</hi> of a towne or pariſh, there ſuch a <hi>Borſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Tythingman,</hi> or any of the reſt, hath nothing to doe with it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:27340:23"/>And thus, hauing opened, ſo ſhortly, and plainly, as I could the duties of all theſe ſaid miniſters of the peace, I doe ſhut vp this worke: deſiring thoſe that ſhall take any profit of this labour, to yéelde thanks to God the moſt liberall giuer.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>FOr the more eaſe of euerie of theſe <hi>Officers,</hi> in finding out of that which belongeth to them, I haue diuided this Treatiſe before into thrée and fortie <hi>Articles</hi> (or parts) by which ech of theſe <hi>Officers</hi> may readily come to all that which belongeth to his owne charge, if he will marke this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble following: for,</p>
               <p>The <hi>High Conſtable</hi> of the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,</hi> Franchiſe, or Wapentake, hath to deale with al thoſe matters that be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined within any of theſe Articles, that is to ſay,</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:27340:24"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Articles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>concerning</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>His name.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>His beginning.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11.12.13.14.15.</cell>
                        <cell>The Peace to bée kept: and ſeruing of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16.17.18.19. 20 21.22.23.</cell>
                        <cell>Execution of Statutes: Phyſicians: Puruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors: Rogues: Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24.25.26 27.28.29.30.43.</cell>
                        <cell>Priſoners: Poore: Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Seſſions: Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: High waies: Poore: High waies.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Conſtable</hi> of a Towne, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh hath his part in all ſuch things as be expreſſed in any of theſe <hi>Articles:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Articles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>concerning</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>His name and beginning.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11.12.13.14.15.16.17.18.19.20.21.22.23.</cell>
                        <cell>Kéeping of the Peace: Seruing of warrants: Execution of ſtatutes: Phyſicians: Puruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors: Rogues: Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:27340:24"/>24.25.26.31.32.33.34.35.36.37.38.39.40.41.42.43.</cell>
                        <cell>Priſoners: Collectors for the Poore: Seruants or labourers: Rogues: Highwaies: Weights and meaſures: Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize: Vnlawfull games: Bridges: Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels: Hats and Caps.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>And euerie <hi>Borſholder, Tythingman, Borochead, Headboroe, Thirdboroe,</hi> and chiefe pledge, may for his <hi>Boroe,</hi> or <hi>Tything,</hi> learne his office by theſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Articles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>concerning</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5.6 7.8.9.</cell>
                        <cell>His name: Beginning: firſt Office: latter Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10.11.12.13.14.15.16.17.18.19.20.21.22.23.</cell>
                        <cell>Kéeping of the Peace: Seruing of warrants: Execution of ſtatutes: Phyſicians: Puruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors: Rogues: Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31.32.33.34.35.36.43.</cell>
                        <cell>Seruants and laborers: Rogues: Highwaies.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:27340:25"/>
            <head>THE DVTIE OF CHVRCHWAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENS.</head>
            <p>WHileſt I paſſed through ſom of the ſtatutes before, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Offices of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable</hi> &amp; <hi>Borſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lder,</hi> I found them mingled with diuers duties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to the <hi>Churchwardens</hi> of pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes: the <hi>Surueiours</hi> of the highwaies: the <hi>Diſtributors</hi> of the prouiſion for the deſtruction of vermine: the <hi>Collectors</hi> and <hi>Ouerſeers</hi> for the poore: &amp; the <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> for the houſes of <hi>Correction:</hi> whereby I was alſo moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to adde ſomewhat of theſe <hi>Offices,</hi> the rather bicauſe I was perſuaded, that with that little more of labour, I might doe a great deale more of good, ſeeing that thereby the plaine countrie man ſhould (after a ſort) be furniſhed with all maner of vnderſtanding (in the temporall lawe) néedfull for the exerciſe of any of thoſe offices that may lightly fall vpon him.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I will ſpeake of the <hi>Churchwardens</hi> office, but that ſo farre
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27340:25"/>
foorth onelie, as the common lawes and ſtatute Lawes of the <hi>Realme</hi> doe leade me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> knowing, that ſuch other parts of that <hi>Office,</hi> as doe reſt vpon the Lawes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> be from tune to time ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently both taught and called vpon, by thoſe that haue the <hi>Execution</hi> of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Churchwardens</hi> of Pariſhes be taken (in fauour of the Church) to be for ſome purpoſes a maner of Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the common law: that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Office of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law.</note> 
               <hi>Perſons enabled by that name, to take mooueable goods or cattels, and to ſue, and be ſued at the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo.</note> 
               <hi>concerning ſuch goods for the vſe and profite of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> And therefore, a man may well in his life time giue, or by his laſt will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qeath mony, or other moueable things to the Churchwardens, or to the pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners of a pariſh, either for the repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their <hi>Church,</hi> or towards the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of bookes,<note place="margin">Li. Intra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol. 576.</note> Communion cuppes, Linnéen clothes, or other decent orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or furniture for the Church. Which maney of gift is ſo much fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Lawe, that it is not altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther néedfull, in ſuch a gift, for a man to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27340:26"/>
vſe to expreſſe words or writing. For if a man doe buie a <hi>Bell,</hi> and doe hang it vp in the Stéeple, or doe make a Pewe, and doe ſet it vp in the <hi>Church,</hi> and doe neither make any worde or writing thereof, yet is this Bell,<note place="margin">11. H. 4. cap. 12.8. H. 7. cap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or Pewe, by this dedicated or giuen to the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">They ſhall haue Action.</note>
               <hi>2</hi> Now, although <hi>Churchwardens</hi> ſhall haue none <hi>Action</hi> at the common lawe to recouer a legacie, or ſuch other thing which they neuer had: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, if any ſuch goods, or ornaments of the Church be once in their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and cuſtodie,<note place="margin">37. H. 6.30 &amp; 34 11. H. 4. cap. 12.8. E. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> then ſhall they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine an <hi>Appeale</hi> of Robberie againſt him that ſtealeth them, or an <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>Treſpaſſe</hi> againſt him that ſhal wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take them away (though it be the Vicar, or Parſon himſelfe) and the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages that they ſhall recouer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſhall be to the vſe and benefite of the pariſh, and not to their owne vſe.<note place="margin">Fitz. n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> br. 91. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mes. 19. H. 6.66. ad on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But if thoſe <hi>Churchwardens</hi> (from whome the goods were ſo taken) ſhall happen to die, before any <hi>Action</hi> by them brought for the goods, yet ſhall the next Churchwardens haue <hi>Action</hi> for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27340:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> And forſomuch as theſe <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens be officers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They may not waſte the Church goods.</note> 
               <hi>put in truſt for the behoofe of their pariſh,</hi> therefore alſo are they not enabled with any other power, than for the good and profite of the pariſh. So that <hi>Churchwardens</hi> can neither giue awaie, nor releaſe, at their owne pleaſure, the goods of the <hi>Church.</hi> For if the <hi>Pariſhioners</hi> ſhall finde that they doe vnprofitably waſte, or miſpende the goods of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> then may they remoue ſuch <hi>church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens,</hi> by making their choice of new:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> E. 4.6</note> which new <hi>Officers</hi> may (by <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of account) call to account the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Churchwardens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They may be remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and braught to account.</note> and ſhall thereby compell them, both to giue reckoning of their doings during their office, and alſo to make ſatiſfaction to the vſe of the <hi>Pariſh</hi> for the harme that it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by their fault. And although the vſage and cuſtome of the <hi>Pariſh</hi> be, that the <hi>Churchwardens</hi> there ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their <hi>Office,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. 8. p. 5.</note> by the ſpace of one whole yéere or two yéeres, or more (as indéed ſom <hi>Pariſhes</hi> haue ſuch cuſtoms) yet vpon ſuch, or the like miſdemeanor
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27340:27"/>
found in them, may the pariſhioners at all times procéed to an Election of new <hi>Churchwardens,</hi> and may remooue the olde, for that otherwiſe they haue no meane by our Lawe to call them to their <hi>Account,</hi> but by ſuch as ſhalbe put in their place. Neuertheleſſe, thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Churchwardens</hi> ſhal (vpon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſuch their <hi>Account</hi>) haue allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of all néedefull ſummes of money, or other things, which they haue expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, either vpon the reparation of the body of the <hi>Church,</hi> or for the prouiſion of méet and lawfull ornaments, or other furniture of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Pariſh:</hi> bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are compellable (by the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Lawes) ſo to lay foorth the goods of the pariſh committed to their cuſtodie and charge. They ſhall haue allowance alſo (vpon ſuch their <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi>) of the money paied by them for reléefe of priſoners in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon gaole, by vertue of the Statute 14. <hi>Eli. caep.</hi> 5. and of whatſoeuer other thing that they are by lawe chargeable to doe.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">They haue not to do with lands.</note>
               <hi>4</hi> This (in effect) is the power and charge that the common Law doth giue to <hi>Churchwardens:</hi> for, as touching any
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27340:27"/>
eſtate in lands, or the profites of any lands, <hi>Churchwardens</hi> haue not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle at all: inſomuch, that if the walles, windowes, or doores of the <hi>Church,</hi> be broken, or the trées in the <hi>Churchyarde</hi> be cut downe, or the graſſe therof be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp, then the Parſon, or Vicar (and not the <hi>Churchwardens</hi>) ſhall haue the <hi>Action</hi> for it:<note place="margin">11. H. 4. cap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12. H. 7. cap. 27.23. H. 7. cap. 9.</note> bicauſe <hi>Churchwardens</hi> are not by Lawe allowed to be a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration for any other thing,<note place="margin">Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens office by the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</note> than for mooueable goods onelie. Now therefore I will ſhew how their office is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a fewe Statute lawes, that doe concerne the ſame.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eliz. cap. 2.</note>
               <hi>5</hi> All perſons inhabiting within the <hi>Queenes</hi> Maieſties dominion,<note place="margin">Repaire to the Church.</note> ſhal dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and faithfully (hauing no lawful or reaſonable excuſe to be abſent) ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor themſelues to reſort to their pariſh <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Chappell</hi> accuſtomed, or (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſonable let thereof) to ſome vſual place where common praier and ſuch ſeruice of God (<hi>as is conteined in the booke of common praier</hi>) ſhall be vſed in ſuch time of let, vpon euery <hi>Sunday</hi> and other daies ordeined and vſed to be kept as <hi>holie daies:</hi> and then and there
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27340:28"/>
to abide orderly and ſoberly, during the time of the common praier, preachings, or other ſeruice of God, there to be vſed and miniſtred, vpon paine of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the Church, and alſo vpon paine that euery perſon ſo offending ſhall forfait for euery ſuch offence xij.d. to be leuied by the <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens</hi> of the pariſh where ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhal be done, to the vſe of the poore of the ſame pariſh, of the goods, lands, and tenements of ſuch offendor, by way of diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">High waies.</note>
               <hi>6</hi> The <hi>Conſtables</hi> and <hi>Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> of euery pariſh ſhall yéerely vpon the Tueſday or Wedneſday in <hi>Eaſter</hi> wéeke,<note place="margin">2 &amp; 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5. El. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> call togither a number of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, and ſhal then elect and chooſe two honeſt perſons of the pariſh to be <hi>Surueiors</hi> and orderers of the works for one yeere for amendemint of the <hi>Highwaies</hi> in their pariſh, leading to any <hi>Market</hi> Towne: which perſons ſhall take vpon them the execution of their ſaid offices, vpon paine, euery of them making default to forfaite xx. s. And the ſaide <hi>Conſtables</hi> and <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens</hi> ſhall then alſo name and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27340:28"/>
               <hi>ſixe daies</hi> for the amendement of the ſaid highwaies before <hi>Midſummer</hi> then next following: and ſhall openly in the <hi>Church</hi> the next Sunday after <hi>Eaſter</hi> giue knowledge of the ſame ſixe daies. And they alſo ought to haue one part of the <hi>Eſtreates</hi> indented, and ſhall call the <hi>Conſtables</hi> to account, &amp;c. <hi>as it doth appeere before in the 30. Article of the Conſtables office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>See after alſo in the office of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiors of the High waies, for leuieng thoſe forfaitures, by the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, if the Surueiors ſhall not leuie and imploie the ſame within one yeere after the offence committed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">5. Eliz 5</note>
               <hi>7</hi> If any perſon within this Realme ſhall (without lawfull licence) eate any fleſh vppon any daies now vſually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued as fiſhdaies,<note place="margin">Eat fleſh.</note> or ſhall vppon any <hi>Wedneſday</hi> now newly limited to be obſerued as <hi>Fiſhday,</hi> haue aboue one diſh of fleſh, for which alſo he ſhall then haue thrée ſeuerall diſhes of Sea fiſh, ſhall forfaite thrée poundes for euery ſuch offence, or elſe ſuffer thrée moneths impriſonment. And euery perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27340:29"/>
whoſe houſe any ſuch offence ſhall be done, &amp; being priuie or knowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and not effectuallye diſcloſing the ſame to ſome <hi>Publike Officer</hi> hauing authoritie to puniſh the ſame, ſhall for euerie offence forfaite fortie ſhillings: the third part of all which forfaitures ſhall be to the vſe of the <hi>Pariſh</hi> wherein the offence ſhall be, and to be leuied by the <hi>Churchwardens</hi> after any conuicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Licence to eate fleſh.</note>The licence for eating of fleſh,<note place="margin">5. Eliz. cap. 5.</note> to be giuen to any perſon for notorious ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of the <hi>Dioces,</hi> or by the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> ought to be regiſtred (if that ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall continue aboue eight daies after ſuch licence granted) in the <hi>church booke</hi> with the knowledge of one of the <hi>Churchwardens</hi> there: and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie licenced ſhall giue iiij. d. to the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> for the entrie thereof.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> In euerie pariſh,<note place="margin">8. Eliz. ca. 15. &amp; 14. Eli. cap. 11.</note> the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,<note place="margin">Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vermine.</note> with ſixe other pariſhioners (to be required by the Churchwardens) ſhall yéerly in one of the holydaies in Eaſter wéeke, and at euery other time when it ſhall be néedfull, taxe and aſſeſſe euery
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27340:29"/>
perſon hauing the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any lands or tythes within that pariſh, to pay ſuch ſummes of money as they ſhall thinke méete, according to the quantitie of ſuch their lande or tythes. And if any ſuch perſon doe denie to pay the ſame, or doe not pay the ſame (within fourtéene dais next after requeſt thereof made by the Churchwardens, or one of them) then ſuch perſon ſhall forfaite for euery time fiue ſhillings, which (togither with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſſeſed) ſhall he leuied by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of the goodes and cattels of ſuch perſon, to be taken by the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or one of them, the ſame diſtreſſe to be ordered and vſed, as diſtreſſes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for amerciaments in any Léetes. And as well the ſaid ſummes as penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (if any of them be ſo leuied) ſhall be yéerly by the Churchwardens, or one of them, for the time being, deliuered by <hi>Billes</hi> indented to two honeſt and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall perſons of the pariſh which ſhall be elected and appointed by the Churchwardens, and ſhall be named, <hi>The Diſtributors of the prouiſion for the deſtruction of noiſome foule and vermine.</hi> And if the ſaide <hi>Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:27340:30"/>
ſixe perſons, or <hi>Diſtributors,</hi> or any of them, ſhall refuſe or make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in the execution of any part of this act, contrarie to the forme thereof, then ſuch offendor ſhall forfait for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry default fiue pound, the one moitie to the <hi>Queene,</hi> the other to him or them (vſing tillage yéerely within the ſame ſhire) that will ſue therefore in anye court of <hi>Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the reſt of the office of the church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, concerning this matter, ſee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward in the dutie of theſe Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. See alſo in Conſtables, Artic. 25. for the gaole monie to be leuied by church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THE OFFICE OF the SVPERVISORS, Surueiors, or orderers of the works for amending of the Highwaies.</head>
            <p>VPon the ſixe daies appointed for<note place="margin">2. &amp; 3. &amp; Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 8. 5. El. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> working in the High waies in ſuch ſort as is before declared in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27340:30"/>
the ſixt Article of the Churchwardens office, euery perſon for euery Plough land in tillage, or paſture that hée or they ſhall occupie in the ſame pariſh, and euerie other perſon kéeping there a draught or plough, ſhall finde and ſende, at euery day and place to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the amending of the waies in the pariſh as is aforeſaid, one waine or Cart, furniſhed after the cuſtome of the countrie, with Oxen, Horſes, or other cattell, and all other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, méete to carrie thinges conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for that purpoſe, and alſo two able men with the ſame, vppon paine of euery draught making default ten ſhillings. And euery other houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and alſo euery cottager and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of that pariſh, able to labour, and being no hired ſeruant by the yéere, ſhall by themſelues, or one ſufficient la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer for euery of them, vpon euery of the ſaid ſixe daies, worke and trauell in the amendement of the ſaid highwaies, vpon paine of euery perſon making de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault to loſe for euery day twelue pence. And if the carriages of the pariſh or any of them ſhall not be thought néedefull
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27340:31"/>
by the <hi>Superuiſors</hi> to be occupied vpon any of the ſaide daies, that then euery ſuch perſon that ſhoulde haue ſent any ſuch carriage, ſhall ſende to the ſaide worke for euery carriage ſo ſpared two able men there to labour for that day, vpon paine to loſe for euery man not ſo ſent to the ſaide worke twelue pence. And euery perſon and carriage aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, ſhall haue and bring with them ſuch Shouels, Spades, Pickes, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks, and other tooles and inſtruments, as they doe make their owne ditches and fences withall, and ſuch as be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for their ſaid worke. And all the ſaid perſons and carriages ſhall do and kéepe their works, as they ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the ſaide <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> or one of them, eight houres of euery of the ſaid daies, vnleſſe they ſhall be otherwiſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed by the ſaid <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> or one of them.</p>
            <p>From hencefoorth it ſhal and may be lawfull to all and ſingular <hi>Superuiſor</hi> and Superuiſors and orderers of the works for the time being, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of the ſaid highwaies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto elected and appointed, according
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27340:31"/>
to the ſtatute made in the ſeconde and third yéere of King <hi>Philip</hi> and Quéene <hi>Marie,</hi> for the better reparation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of the high waies within their ſeuerall pariſhes &amp; limits where they ſhall be ſo made <hi>Superuiſors</hi> (if it ſhall be ſo to them thought neceſſarie) to take and carrie awaie of the rubbiſh or ſmalleſt broken ſtones of any <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> or Quarries lieng or being within the pariſh where they ſhall be <hi>Superui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> without licence, controllment or impeachment of the owners or owner, ſo much as by their diſcretions ſhall bée déemed and iudged neceſſarie to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of the ſaid waies. And that for default of any ſuch <hi>Quarry</hi> or Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, it ſhall and may be lawfull to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch <hi>Superuiſor,</hi> or Superuiſors, for the vſe aforeſaid, in the ſeueral grounds of any perſon or perſons, being within the pariſh, and limits where they ſhall be <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> and nigh adioining to the waie or waies wherein ſuch repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſhall be thought neceſſarie to be made, and wherein grauell, ſand, or ſinder is likely to be founde, to digge or cauſe to be digged, for grauell, ſand, or
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27340:32"/>
ſinder, and likewiſe to gather ſtones li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng vpon any lands or grounds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the pariſh, and méete to be vſed to ſuch ſeruice and purpoſe, and thereof to take and carrie away ſo much as by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the ſaid Superuiſors ſhall be thought neceſſarie to be imploied in the amendment of the ſaid highwaies. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alwaies that it ſhall not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to any ſuch <hi>Superuiſor,</hi> or Superui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, by vertue of this act, to cauſe any rubbiſh to be digged out of any <hi>Quarrie</hi> or Quarries, but onelie ſhall extend to ſuch rubbiſh as ſhall be found there rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die digged by the owner or owners of the ſaide quarrie or quarries, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by his or their licence and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, nor ſhall not extend to giue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to any <hi>Superuiſor</hi> or Superui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors to digge, or cauſe to be digged, any grauell, ſand, or ſinder in the houſe, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, orcharde, or medowe, of any perſon or perſons, nor that it ſhall be lawfull by this act to any ſuch <hi>Superuiſor</hi> or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruiſors to cauſe any more pits to bée digged for grauell in any ſeuerall and incloſed ground than one only, and that the ſame pit or hole ſo digged for grauel
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27340:32"/>
as is aforeſaide, ſhall not by any waie be in breadth or length aboue ten yards at the moſt. And that euery ſuch <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſor</hi> as ſhall cauſe any ſuch pit to be made, and digged for grauell, ſande, or ſinder, as is aforeſaide, ſhall within one moneth next after any ſuch digging or pit made, cauſe the ſame to be filled, and ſtopped vp with earth, at the coſt and charges of the <hi>Pariſhioners,</hi> vpon paine to forfaite to the owner and owners of the ſoile, wherein any ſuch pit ſhall be made and digged, for euery default, fiue marks.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eli. 13.</note>From henceforth, euery ſuch <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſor</hi> and Superuiſors, as is aforeſaid, ſhall by force of this act, within the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or limits where he or they ſhall be <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> haue full power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to turne any ſuch water courſe, or ſpring of water, being in any of the ſaid highwaies, into any ditch, or ditches of the ſeuerall ground or ſoile of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoeuer next adioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſaide waies, in ſuch maner and forme as by the diſcretions of the ſaid <hi>Superuiſors</hi> ſhal be thought méeteſt and conuenient.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:27340:33"/>Such <hi>Superuiſor,</hi> or Superuiſors, for the time being within one moneth next after default or offence made, done, or committed by any perſon or perſons, contrarie to the prouiſion, purport, and true meaning of the ſtatute made (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning highwaies) in the ſeconde and third yéere of King <hi>Philip</hi> and Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> ſhall preſent euery ſuch default or offence to the next <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace for the time being, vpon paine to forfeit for euery ſuch default and offence, in ſuch ſort not by them preſented, xl. s.</p>
            <p>Euery perſon or perſons (except ſuch as ſhall dwell in the Citie of <hi>London</hi>) that ſhall be aſſeſſed to the paiment of any <hi>Subſidie</hi> to hir Maieſtie to fiue <abbr>l</abbr>. in goods, or fortie ſhillings in lands, or aboue, during all ſuch time as he ſhall ſtand ſo aſſeſſed &amp; not altered, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none of the parties chargeable for the amendement of highwaies by any former law, but as a Cottager, ſhal find two able men yéerely, to labour in the highwaies, at ſuch daies and times, as by the ſeuerall ſtatutes thereof are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and appointed. And euery other that hereafter ſhall occupie a plough
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:27340:33"/>
land in tillage or paſture, lieng and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſeuerall <hi>pariſhes,</hi> ſhall be charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the making of the waies within the pariſh where he dwelleth, as farre foorth, and in ſuch maner and forme, as any perſon hauing a plough land, in any one pariſh, is or ought to be chargeable, by reaſon of the ſaid former ſtatutes, or either of them. And euerie perſon or perſons, occupieng and kéeping in his or their hands or poſſeſſions, ſeuerall or diuerſe plough lands, as aforeſaid in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall or diuerſe townes, ſhall be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to find in ech towne or pariſh (wher the plough lands being in his occupieng doe lie) one Cart, Waine, Tumbrell, dung Pot, or Court, Sleads, Carres, or Dragges, furniſhed for the amendment and repairing of the highwaies within the ſeuerall pariſhes where the ſaide plough lands doe lie, in ſuch maner and forme, as if he or they were a Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner dwelling within the pariſhes, wher the ſame ſeuerall plough lands doe lie.</p>
            <p>Euery perſon or perſons, that ſhall not repaire, ditch, or ſcowre any haies, fences, ditches, or hedges adioining to any high way or common fairing way,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27340:34"/>
or ſhall not cut downe or kéepe lowe all trees and buſhes, growing in or next adioining to any the ſaide waies accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true intent &amp; meaning of the act made in the fift yéere of the Quéenes Maieſtie reigne that now is, for euerie offence committed therein, contrarie to the true intent thereof, ſhall forfuit and loſe for euery default ten ſhillings And all and euerie perſon and perſons that ſhal occupie any lands adioining to the ſaid ground, ſo adioining to any ſuch high way, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon fairing way, where any ditching or ſcouring ſhuld or ought to be as aforeſaide, ſhall from time to time, as néed ſhall require, ditch or ſcowre in his and their ground ſo adioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereby the water conueied from the ſaid high waie, or common fairing waie, ouer the ground next adioining, may haue paſſage ouer the ſaid ground, ſo next adioining to that ground, vpon paine of forfaiture for euerie time ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, for euerie roode not ſo ditched and ſcowred, xij.d.</p>
            <p>No perſon or perſons hauing any ground by leaſe or otherwiſe, adioining to any high waie, or common fairing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:27340:34"/>
waie, leading to any market Towne, ſhal caſt or ſcowre any ditch, &amp; throwe or lay the ſoyle thereof into the high waie, and ſuffer it to lie there by the ſpace of ſix moneths to the annoiance of the ſaid high waie, or common fairing waie, vpon paine of forfeiture for euery load of ſoyle, ſo caſt into the high waie, or common fairing waie, in ditching or ſcowring, xij.d. And where any hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue béen ſo caſt into the high way, or common fairing waie, that there is a banke betwéene the ſaide waie and the ditch, it ſhall be lawfull for the <hi>Suruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors</hi> and workemen, by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, appointed for the amendment of the ſaide waies, to make ſtuces or other deuiſes by their diſcretions, to conuey the water out of the ſaid waie into the ditch: any lawe, right, intereſt, cuſtome, or vſage to the contrarie notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Euerie penaltie, ſumme or ſummes of monie forfeited for any cauſe within this ſtatute, ſhall be leuied in euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by the <hi>Suruciors</hi> of the waies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that pariſh for the time being, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, &amp; ſale of diſtreſſe, in manner and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27340:35"/>
forme as fines or amerciaments in <hi>Leetes</hi> haue béene vſed, and the monie ſo leuied, to be imploied vppon the high waie, or common fairing waie where the offence was committed. And if the <hi>Surueiors</hi> ſhall not or wil not leuie and imploy the ſame within one yéere after the offence ſo committed, that then the ſaide ſumme or ſummes, forfaiture or forfaitures, ſhall be leuied in forme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide, by the <hi>Conſtables</hi> or <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens</hi> of the towne or pariſh where the worke ought to be done in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie (as aforeſaide) and that he or they ſo leuieng any of the ſaid penalties or forfaitures, ſhall make and yéeld ſuch account as is appointed in the before recited ſtatutes, or either of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THE OFFICE OF the DISTIBVTERS of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for the deſtruction of noiſome foule and Vermine.</head>
            <p>THeſe <hi>Diſtributers</hi> being ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,<note place="margin">8. Eliz. ca. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 14. Eli cap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and hauing monie (<hi>as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhewed in the</hi> 8. <hi>Article of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27340:35"/>
the Churchwardens office</hi>) ſhall giue and pay of the ſame monie ſo to them deliuered to euerie perſon that ſhall bring to them any heads of old Crows, Choughs, Pies, or Rookes, taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſeuerall pariſhes, for the heads of euerie thrée of them a penie: and for the hends of euerie ſixe yoong Crowes, Choughs, Pies, or Rookes taken, as is aforeſaide a penie, and for euerie ſixe egges of any of them vnbroken a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: and likewiſe for euerie xii. Stares heads a penie. All which ſaid heads and egges, the ſaid <hi>Diſtributers</hi> in ſom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place ſhall kéepe, and ſhall eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie moneth at the leaſt bring foorth the ſame before the ſaide <hi>Churchwardens</hi> and taxors, or thrée of them, and then and there to them ſhall make a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in writing, what mony they haue laied foorth and paid for ſuch heade and egges, and for the heads of ſuch other rauenous birds and vermine, as are hereafter in this act mentioned. That is to ſaie: for euerie head of Merton, Haukes, Furſekite, Moldkite, Buſſard, Schagge, Carmerant, or Ringtaile two pence, and for euerie two egges of them
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27340:36"/>
a penie: for euerie Iron or Oſpraie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> head, iiii.d. for the head of euery Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Pie, Iay, Rauen, or Kite, a penie: for the head of euerye birde, which is called the Kings Fiſher, a penie: for the head of euery Bulfinch, or other bird that deuoureth the blouth of fruit, one penie: for the heads of euery Foxe, or Grey, twelue pence: and for the head of euery Fichew, Polcat, Weſell, Stote, Faire, Badge, or Wilde cat, a penie: for the heads of euerie Otter, or Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hogs, ii.d. for the heads of euery thrée Rats, or twelue Mice, a penie: for the heads of euery Moldwarpe, or Want an halfe penie: for the heads of euery which birds and vermine laſt mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the laſt <hi>Diſtributers</hi> ſhall likewiſe pay and giue to the bringer of them, for euery head kild and taken within their ſeuerall pariſh, as before is limited, and ſhall kéepe the ſame to be ſhewed foorth vpon their account in maner and forme as is aforeſaide. All which ſaide heads and egges ſhall be foorthwith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch account made in the preſence of the ſaid <hi>Churchwardens,</hi> and Tarors or of thrée of them, burned, conſumed,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:27340:36"/>
or cut in ſunder. And if vpon any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to be made, in the end and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the office of any ſuch <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributers,</hi> it ſhall appéere that any ſumme of money is remaining in the hands of the ſaide <hi>Diſtributers,</hi> or any of them: then the ſame ſhall be by <hi>Bill</hi> indented, as is aforeſaide, deliuered ouer to ſuch perſons, as be or ſhall be elected to the ſame <hi>Office,</hi> for the yéere next following, by them to be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as is aforeſaide. This ſhall not in any wiſe extende, to giue any libertie or authoritie to any perſon or perſons, to vſe or exerciſe any meanes or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for the deſtruction of Crowes, or Rookes, Choughes, or other the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine aforeſaide in any place or places, to the diſturbance, let, or deſtruction of the building or breeding of any kinde of Hawkes, Herons, Egrittes, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Swannes, or Shouelers: or to the hurt and deſtruction of any Dooues, Doouehouſes, Déere, or Warren of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, nor extend to giue or appoint any ſumme or ſummes of mony to be giuen paid, or diſtributed, to any perſon or perſons, for the head or heads of any
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27340:37"/>
Buſſard, Ringtaile, Herne, Polcat, Fitchew, or Stote, taken in any <hi>Parke, Warren,</hi> or ground imploied to the maintenance of any game of Conies, or to any Stares taken in doouehouſes, nor to the killing or bringing the head of any Kite or Rauen, killed in any Citie or Towne Corporate, or within two miles of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THE OFFICE AND dutie of the COLLECTORS, and Ouerſeers for the poore, ſetled in their abiding places.</head>
            <p>THe Iuſtices of Peace in all the ſhires of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> and the Maiors, Bailifes, Shirifes,<note place="margin">14. Eli. 5 &amp; 18. El. cap 3.</note> and other officers of the Cities, Boroughes, and Franchiſes whereof they be Iuſtices of Peace, hauing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed within the limits of their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral authorities conuenient abiding pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for ſetling of the poore people, and hauing alſo aſſeſſed the inhabitants within the ſame limits towardes a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27340:37"/>
wéekely contribution for the reléefe of the ſame poore people, ought then alſo to appoint <hi>Collectors</hi> and Ouerſéers for one whole yéere: which ſaid <hi>Collectors</hi> ſhall gather the ſaid wéekely contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſhal make deliuerie of ſo much thereof to the ſaid poore people, as the ſaid Iuſtices, Maiors, Shirifes, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifes, and other officers ſhall appoint them. And if the ſaid <hi>Ouerſeers</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be ouerſéers, then euery of them ſo offending ſhall forfaite ten ſhillings for euerie ſuch default. And if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo appointed to be <hi>Collector,</hi> ſhall refuſe the ſaid office, or ſhall (after hée hath agréed to it) neglect the ſame, he ſhal loſe for euerie offence to the vſe of the poore of the ſame place, xl. ſhillings.</p>
            <p>The ſaide <hi>Collectors,</hi> and euery of them, ſo to be choſen, as is aforeſaide, ſhall make their iuſt account halfe yéer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their ſaid collection and gathering, to two <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the Peace, dwelling next the ſaide abiding place or places, not being within any Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate: or to the Maiors or other chiefe Officers of ſuch Cities or Townes corporate, and when they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:27340:38"/>
go out of their <hi>Offices,</hi> they ſhall deliuer or cauſe to be deliuered foorthwith vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their accounts, all ſuch ſurpluſages of their <hi>Collection</hi> and gathering, as ſhall then remaine vndiſtributed to be ordered by the ſaide <hi>Iuſtices,</hi> Maiors, Bailifes, or other head Officers, vpon the paine of teane pounds. If any ſuch <hi>Collector</hi> ſhall refuſe to make his ſaide account, or neglect the ſame by the ſpace of fourtéene daies after requeſt to him therefore made: then the ſaid two <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,</hi> or one of them, may commit the ſaid <hi>Collector</hi> to the next <hi>Gaole</hi> in the ſaide Countie, there to remaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Baile</hi> or <hi>Mainpriſe,</hi> til he haue made his ſaid account, and immediate pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and deliuerie of all ſuch <hi>Suſplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> as he hath receiued.</p>
            <p>No perſon or perſons, hauing charge of anye voyage in paſſing from the Realme of <hi>Irelande,</hi> or from the Iſle of <hi>Man</hi> into this Realme of <hi>Englande,</hi> doe wittingly, or willingly tranſport, bring carrie or conueigh, or ſuffer to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, brought, carried, or conueighed, in any ſhip, picarde, veſſell, boate, or boates, from and out of the ſaid Realme
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:27340:38"/>
of <hi>Irelande,</hi> or from, or out of the ſaide Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> into the Realme of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> or any part thereof, any Vagabond, Rogue, or Begger, or any ſuch as ſhall be forced, or very like, to liue by begging within the Realmes of <hi>Englande</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> being borne in the Realme of <hi>Irelande,</hi> or in the ſaide Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> on paine of euery ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo bringing, tranſporting, carrieng and conueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either ſuffering to be brought, tranſported, carried, and conueighed in manner and forme aforeſaide, to forfeite and looſe for euerie ſuch Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond, Rogue, Begger, or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which ſhall be forced, or like to liue by begging within this Realme of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> being tranſported, and ſet on lande in any part of <hi>England</hi> or of <hi>Wales,</hi> twentie ſhillings of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Engliſh money, to the vſe of the <hi>Poore</hi> of the ſame pariſh in which they were ſet on lande, to be leuied by the <hi>Collectors</hi> of the ſame poore for the time being, by ſeiſure and ſelling of any of the goods and cattels of the ſame perſon which ſhall ſo bring, tranſport, carrie,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:27340:39"/>
or conueigh, any ſuch Rogue, Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond, or begger, or other perſon which ſhall be forced, or like to liue by beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, within the Realme of <hi>England</hi> or of <hi>Wales,</hi> to the value of the ſame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faiture.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THE OFFICE OF the COLLECTORS and Gouernors of the poore.</head>
            <p>IN euerie <hi>Citie</hi> and Towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate within this <hi>Realme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">18. Eliz. cap. 3.</note> a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſtore and ſtock of Wool, Hempe Flaxe, Iron, or other ſtuffe by the appeintment of the <hi>Maior,</hi> Bailifes, Iuſtices, or other head <hi>Officers,</hi> hauing rule in the ſaid <hi>Cities,</hi> or Townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate (of themſelues, and of other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants within their ſeuerall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, to be taxed, leuied, and gathered) ſhall be prouided. And that likewiſe, in euerie other <hi>Market</hi> Towne or other place, within any countrie of this <hi>Realme,</hi> (whereto the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the Peace, or greater part of them, in their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:27340:39"/>
generall <hi>Seſſions</hi> yéerely next after <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> within euerie limit ſhalbe thought méete and conuenient) a like competent ſtore and ſtocke of Wooll, Flax, Iron, or other ſtuffe, as the countrie is moſt méete for, by appointment and order of the ſaid <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of peace, or the greater part of them at their generall <hi>Seſſions,</hi> (of all the inhabitants within their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall authorities, to be taxed, leuied, and gathered) ſhall be prouided. The ſaid ſtores and ſtocks, in ſuch <hi>Cities</hi> and Townes corporate, to be committed to the hands and cuſtodie of ſuch perſons, as ſhall by the <hi>Maior,</hi> Bailifes, <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> or other head Officers, hauing au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in euerie ſuch <hi>Citie</hi> or Towne corporate, be appointed: and in other townes and places, to ſuch perſons, as to the ſaide <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of peace, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of them in their ſaide generall <hi>Seſſions</hi> of the Peace in their ſeuerall Counties, ſhall be by them appointed. Which ſaide perſons ſo appointed, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſhall haue power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (by the aduiſe of them who doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them, to diſpoſe, order, and giue rules, for the diuiſion and manner of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:27340:40"/>
working of the ſaide ſtocks and ſtores, who ſhall from hencefoorth be called, <hi>the Collectors and Gouernours of the Poore</hi> to the intent euery ſuch poore and needie perſon, olde or yoong, able to doe any worke, ſtanding in neceſſitie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe, ſhall not for want of worke go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, either begging, or committing priferings, or other miſdemeanour, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in idleneſſe: which <hi>Collectours</hi> and <hi>Gouernors</hi> of the poore, from time to time (as cauſe requireth) ſhall and may of the ſame ſtocke and ſtore, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſuch poore and néedie perſon, a competent portion, to be wrought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yarne or other matter, within ſuch time, and in ſuch ſort, as in their diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall be from time to time limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prefixed, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being wrought, to be from time to time deliuered to the ſaid <hi>Collectors</hi> and <hi>Gouernors</hi> of the poore: for which they ſhall make paiment to them that worke the ſame, according to the deſert of the worke: and ſhall of new deliuer more to be wrought, and ſo from time to time to deliuer ſtuffe vnwrought, and to receiue the ſame againe wrought, as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:27340:40"/>
oft as cauſe ſhal require: which Hempe, Wooll, Flaxe, or other ſtuffe, wrought, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time ſhall be ſold by the ſaid <hi>Collectors</hi> and Gouernors of the poore, either at ſome <hi>Market,</hi> or other place, &amp; at ſuch time as they ſhall thinke méet, and with the money comming of the ſale, to buy more ſtuffe, in ſuch wiſe as the ſtocks or ſtore ſhal not be decaied in value. And if hereafter any ſuch perſon able to do any ſuch worke, ſhal refuſe to work, or ſhal go abroad begging, or liue idlely, or taking ſuch worke ſhall ſpoile or imbeſell the ſame, in ſuch wiſe, that (after monition giuen) the <hi>Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Churchwardens</hi> of the pariſh, and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors</hi> and Gouernors of the poóre, or the more part of them, ſhall thinke the ſame perſon not méete to haue any more work deliuered out of the ſame ſtore or ſtocke, that then vpon <hi>Certificat</hi> made vnder their hands, and brought by one of the ſaide <hi>Collectors</hi> and Gouernors of the poore, to the hands of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons as ſhall in that Countie haue the ouerſight and gouernement of one of the houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient apparell méete for ſuch a bodie
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:27340:41"/>
to weare, he, ſhe, or they, from ſuch towne, place or pariſh ſhall be receiued into ſuch houſes of correction, there to be ſtreitly kept, as well in diet, as in worke, and alſo puniſhed from time to time, as to the ſaid perſons, hauing the ouerſight and gouernement of the ſaide houſe of <hi>Correction</hi> ſhall be appointed, as hereafter is declared. All which ſtocks and ſtores, ſhall be prouided and deliuered to the hands of the ſaide <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors</hi> and Gouernours of the poore, at all times hereafter as occaſion ſhall ſerue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THE DVTIES OF the CENSORS (or Wardens) and of the Collectors for the houſes of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</head>
            <p>WIthin euerie countie of this Realme, one, two,<note place="margin">18. Eli. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or more <hi>Abiding</hi> houſes, or places conuenient in ſome <hi>Market</hi> Towne, or Corporate Towne, or other place or places, by purchaſe, leaſe, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:27340:41"/>
or otherwiſe, by the appointment and order of the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, or the more part of them in their generall Seſſions (of the inhabitants within their ſeuerall authorities to be taxed, leuied, and gathered) ſhall be prouided, and called <hi>the houſe, or houſes of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection:</hi> and alſo ſtocke and ſtore, and implements, to be in like ſort alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, for ſetting on worke and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not onlie of thoſe which by the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors</hi> and Gouernors of the poore, for cauſes aforeſaid to the ſaide houſes of Correction, ſhall be brought, but alſo of ſuch as be, or ſhall be inhabiting in no pariſh, or be, or ſhalbe taken as Rogues, or once puniſhed as Rogues, and by reaſon of the vncerteintie of their birth, or of their dwelling by the ſpace of three yéeres, or for any other cauſe, ought to be abiding and kept within the ſame Countie: which ſaid <hi>Houſe,</hi> or houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> with ſtocks, ſtores, and implements appointed for ſuch houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> ſhall be prouided in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Countie, within ſuch time as to the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, or the more part of them, in their ſaide generall <hi>Seſſions</hi> of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:27340:42"/>
the peace in euerie Countie, within their ſeuerall iuriſdictions, ſhall bée thought meete and conuenient, ſo as it excéed not two yéeres after taxation in ſuch Countie for that purpoſe made, or elſe the money leuied to be repaied: and that euerie perſon refuſing to pay, or not paieng ſuch ſumme of money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the making, obteining, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of the ſaide houſes of <hi>Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and buieng of ſtocks, and ſtores, and for the reléefe and ſuſtentation of ſuch perſons as ſhall be appointed to the ſaid houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> as vpon them or any of them, ſhal be (by order aforeſaid) taxed, and at ſuch time (as by the ſame order ſhall be appointed) ſhall for euery default forfeite double ſo much as he or they ſhall be ſo tared vnto. And the ſaid Iuſtices of Peace, or the more part of them in their ſaid generall Seſſions in euery Countie, ſhall and may appoint from time to time, perſons which ſhall be <hi>Ouerſeers</hi> of euery ſuch houſe of <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> which ſaid perſons ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Cenſors and Wardens of the houſes of Correction,</hi> and ſhall haue the rule, gouernement, and order of ſuch
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:27340:42"/>
houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> according to ſuch orders as by the ſaid <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Peace, or the more part of them, in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Seſſions</hi> in euery Countie, ſhall be preſcribed. And the ſaid Iuſtices ſhall alſo appoint others for the gathering of ſuch money, as ſhall be taxed vpon any perſon or perſons within their ſeuerall iuriſdictions, towards the maintenance of the ſaide houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> which ſhalbe called <hi>the Collectors for the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of correction:</hi> and if any perſon or perſons refuſe to be <hi>Collector</hi> and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the poore, or <hi>Cenſor</hi> &amp; War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or Collector of or for any the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> euery perſon ſo refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſhall forfait and loſe the ſumme of fiue pound. And all and ſingular perſon and perſons, appointed by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this act to be any <hi>Collector</hi> and Gouernour of the poore, or <hi>Cenſor</hi> and warden, or <hi>Collector</hi> for any the houſes of <hi>Correction</hi> in any Countie, Citie, Towne corporate, or other place in this <hi>Realme,</hi> ſhall as often as they or any of them ſhall be called thereto by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hauing the appointment of them, make a iuſt account of all ſuch ſumme
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:27340:43"/>
or ſummes of money or other things, as they or any of them haue gathered, had, or raiſed in commoditie, within their ſeuerall collections or charge: and if any ſuch <hi>Collector</hi> or Gouernour of the poore, <hi>Collector, Cenſor,</hi> or <hi>Warden</hi> of or for the houſes of <hi>Correction,</hi> refuſe to make ſuch account, or neglect the ſame by the ſpace of xiiij. daies next after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt therefore to him made, or ſhal not within one wéeke after ſuch account rendered, yéeld and pay the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rearages, which he or they (vpon ſuch account) ſhall be found in, to ſuch perſon or perſons, as they ſhall be appointed vnto, by them before whom their ſaide account ſhall be taken: that then the ſaid <hi>Collector, gouernor, Cenſor,</hi> or <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> to be committed to any vſual gaole within the ſaide Countie, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine without baile or mainpriſe, till he haue made his account and paiment of ſuch arrearages as he hath receiued: vpon the making of which account, it ſhall and may be lawful to ſuch perſons as haue the appointment of the ſaide <hi>Collectors</hi> and Gouernors of the poore, <hi>Cenſors,</hi> Wardens and <hi>Collectors</hi> of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:27340:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the houſes of <hi>Correction</hi> (euery of them within their authoritie) to allow, aſwel ſuch reaſonable allowance to euery the ſaid <hi>Collectors</hi> and Gouernours of the poore, <hi>Cenſors,</hi> Wardens and Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the houſes of <hi>correction,</hi> for ſuch money as they or any of them haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied or diſburſed in the execution of the ſaid ſeuerall offices, as alſo ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fées and wages for their paines taken in that behalfe, as to them ſhall bée thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
